Jane Burr Papers, circa 1860s-1958
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Jane Burr Papers
circa 1860s-1958
Burr, Jane, 1882-1958
MS 25
1 box (.5 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Journalist; Poet; Playwright. Papers include articles, photographs, and correspondence from Havelock Ellis, Margaret Sanger, H.G. Wells, Agnes Smedley, Fannie Hurst, Roger Baldwin, and Max Eastman, among others.
Biographical Note
Rosalind Mae Guggenheim, better known as Jane Burr, was born in Cleburne, Texas, December 27, 1882, the daughter of Bertha Kaufman and Leopold Guggenheim. She married Horatio G. Winslow in 1911 and they divorced in 1925. During the 1910s and 20s, she resided in New York City and was part of the Greenwich Village crowd of radicals, artists, and writers. She wrote articles on women's rights, marriage, dress reform, birth control, and changing sexual attitudes. In 1922 she traveled around the world studying and writing articles about the condition of women for United Press. In London she caused a stir by wearing her famous "knickerbockers." Jane Burr published a number of novels, poems and plays. Some of her better known works include City Dust (1917), The Glorious Hope (1918), The Passionate Spectator (1921), Marble and Mud (1935), The Queen is Dead (1938), and Fourteen Radio Plays (1945). Beginning in the 1940s she lived in Woodstock, New York where she opened her farmhouse as an inn for writers and ran an antique shop from her barn. Jane Burr died in 1958.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Jane Burr Papers include articles by and about Burr, photographs of Burr and her family, and about 150 letters to her. There is personal correspondence from Havelock Ellis from 1892-1935, mostly about their common interest in sex reform and the position of women: marriage, divorce, birth control; and a freer attitude toward sex. Other correspondents include Margaret Sanger, H.G. Wells, Agnes Smedley, Fannie Hurst, Roger Baldwin, and Max Eastman. Burr's letters to Margaret Grierson, Director of the Sophia Smith Collection, contain detailed descriptions of her papers and provide valuable biographical context. Descriptions written on the back of the photographs of family and places provide additional biographical information. There are a number of photographs of Burr's home town, Cleburne, Texas.
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Jane Burr (on the suggestion of Margaret Sanger) donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection from 1949 to 1958.
Search Terms
Bohemianism--New York (State)--New York; Clothing and dress--Social aspects--History--20th century--Sources; Jewish women--United States--Biography--Sources; Marriage, Companionate--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women authors, American--20th century--Biography--Sources; Women journalists--United States--Biography--Sources; Baldwin, Roger, 1884-1981--Correspondence; Burr, Jane, pseud.; Eastman, Max--Correspondence; Ellis, Havelock, 1859-1939-Correspondence; Guggenheim family; Hurst, Fannie, 1889-1968-Correspondence; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966--Correspondence; Smedley, Agnes, 1892-1950--Correspondence; Wells, H.G. (Herbert George), 1866-1946--Correspondence; Winslow, Rosalind Mae Guggenheim, 1882-1958
- Contents (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Photographs
  - Jane Burr, alone, circa 1895-1950s, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2a)
  - Family groups, friends, and scenes, circa 1870s-1950s, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2b)
  - Framed portraits of Bertha (mother) and Rosa (aunt) Kaufman, circa 1860s (Box 1, Folder 2c)
- Miscellaneous memorabilia (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Clippings about Jane Burr, 1918-47 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Writings by Jane Burr, 1922-24, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Correspondence to Jane Burr
  - Agronsky, Gershan, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Baldwin, Roger, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Block, Anita, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cohn, Alfred, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Dell, Floyd, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Eastman, Max, 1944, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ellis, Havelock, 1922-35 (Box 1, Folder 12-16)
  - Forrest, Elizabeth, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Freeman, Joseph, 1947, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Goldman, Edwin Frank, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Goldring, Douglas, 1932, 1949, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Hahn, Emily, 1945, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Jonkman, Jeanette, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Hurst, Fannie, 1914, 1947, 1948, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Lane, Rose Wilder, 1932, 1943, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Liverwright, Horace, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Mana-Zucca, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Martin, Helen, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Menninger, William C., 1950 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Michaelis, Karin, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Nordau, Max, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Palmer, Cecil, 1935, 1936, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Rosenblatt, Frank, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Sanger, Margaret, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Smedley, Agnes, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Stefansson, Vilhtalmur, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Untermeyer, Jean Starr, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Weisgard, Runard, 1949, 1950, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Wells, H.G., 1938, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Correspondence from Jane Burr to Margaret Storrs Grierson, 1949-53 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Mildred Sales: excerpt from "Books and Authors," n.d. (Box 1, Folder 40)
- Horatio G. Winslow: divorce papers, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- Framed portrait (drawing) of Jane Burr by Edward C. Caswell, n.d. (oversized) (Box 2)